Frederick Hale Papers
Frederick Hale Papers
1917-1940
Hale, Frederick, 1874-1963.
1.0 linear ft.
Papers of the Legislator. U.S. Senator from Maine, 1917-1941. Correspondence relating to Hale's term in the Senate, and published items.
149028
Biographical History
Frederick Hale (1874-1963) was an American lawyer and United States Senator from Maine formore than thirty years.
Hale was born in Detroit, Michigan, into a political family. His mother was the daughter, wife and mother of United States senators and his father, Eugene Hale, served in the Senate from 1881 to 1911. His maternal grandfather, Zachariah Chandler, was also a member of the Senate. Hale attended preparatory schools in Lawerenceville, New Jersey and Groton, Massachusetts and graduated from Harvard College in 1896. In 1896 and 1897, he attended Columbia Law School. He was admitted to the bar and commenced practice in Portland, Maine in 1899. A conservative Republican and U.S. Senator from Maine from 1917-1941, Hale served on the Senate Appropriations Committee and the Naval Affairs Committee. He never married.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Frederick Hale Papers consist of correspondence, manuscripts and published material. Correspondence includes incoming, correspondence and outgoing correspondence arranged alphabetically by the name of the correspondent. Manuscripts contains two unidentified manuscripts. Published material includes a newspaper clipping about Mr. Hale and a speech by him.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to politics, government, and public administration. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Beveridge, Albert Jeremiah, 1862-1927.; Chavez, Dennis, 1888-1962.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933.; Early, Stephen T. (Stephen Tyree), 1889-1951.; Edge, Walter E. (Walter Evans), 1873-1956.; Ellender, Allen J., 1890-1972.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Hale, Frederick, 1874-1963.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Johnson, Hiram, 1866-1945.; Kellogg, Frank B. (Frank Billings), 1856-1937.; Lejeune, John Archer, 1867-1942.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924.; McCormick, Medill, 1877-1925.; McCumber, Porter J. (Porter James), 1856-1933.; Newberry, Truman Handy, 1864-1945.; Ransdell, Joseph E. (Joseph Eugene), 1858-1954.; Roberts, Kenneth Lewis, 1885-1957.; Roosevelt, Kermit, 1889-1943.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1887-1944.; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Legislators -- United States.; Maine -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1901-1953.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Speeches (documents); Legislators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - A-D, 1921; 1923-1925,; 1927-1930,; 1933-1934,; 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - Austin, Warren, Senator, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Baker, Newton D., 1933 (Box 1)
  - Ball, L. Heisler, Senator, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Barbour, Warren, 1935; 1936,; 1938 (Box 1)
  - Barkley, Alben, Senator, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Beedy, Carroll L., 1932 (Box 1)
  - Beveridge, Albert J., 1924-1926 (Box 1)
  - Bilbo, Theodore G., Senator (Box 1)
  - Bingham, Hiram, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Bowman, Frank L., 1930 (Box 1)
  - Bratton, Sam G., Senator, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Burke, Edward R., Senator, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Capper, Arthtr, Senator, 1923; 1928 (Box 1)
  - Chavez, Dennis, Senator, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Coolidge, Calvin, 1923; 1925,; 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Copeland, Royal S., Senator, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Couzens, James, Senator, 1926; 1935 (Box 1)
  - Cox, Channing, Governor of Massachusetts, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Cummings, Homer, Attorney General, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Cummins, Albert, Senator, 1919; 1921 (Box 1)
  - Daniels, Josephus, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Davies, Joseph E., 1922 (Box 1)
  - Davis, Dwight, Secretary of War, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Davis, James, Senator, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Dill, Clarence, Senator, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Donahey, Vic, Senator, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Dunning, James, 1921; 1929 (Box 1)
  - Early, Stephen, Secretary to President F.D. Roosevelt, 1934-1938 (Box 1)
  - Edge, Walter E., Senator, 1921; 1923,; 1926,; 1930,; 1935 (Box 1)
  - Elkins, Davis, Senator, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Ellender, Allen J., Senator, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - F-K, 1916; 1921-1924,; 1927,; 1929,; 1930,; 1932,; 1936-1939 (Box 1)
  - Farley, James, 1933; 1936 (Box 1)
  - Farrington, W.R., 1928 (Box 1)
  - Fernald, Bert M., Senator, 1921; 1923 (Box 1)
  - Fess, Simeon D., Senator, 1926 (Box 1)
  - France, Joseph I., Senator, 1919; 1921 (Box 1)
  - Frazier, Lynn J., Senator, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Freylinghuysen, Joseph S., Senator, 1921-1922 (Box 1)
  - Gillett, Frederick H., Senator, 1923-1924; 1929,; undated (Box 1)
  - Goff, Guy D., 1927; 1930 (Box 1)
  - Good, James W., 1929 (Box 1)
  - Harrison, Pat, Senator, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Hatfield, H.D., Senator, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Harding, Mr. and Mrs. Warren G., 1920; 1921,; undated (Box 1)
  - Hawes, Harry B., Senator, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Herbert, Felix, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Holt, Rush, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1921; 1928-1930,; 1932 (Box 1)
  - Hughes, Charles E., 1921; 1924 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Hiram W., 1918; 1925,; 1931,; 1936 (Box 1)
  - Jones, Wesley L., Senator, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Kellogg, Frank B., Senator, 1919-1920; undated (Box 1)
  - L-M (Box 2)
  - Latimer, Rear Admiral J.L., 1925-1926 (Box 2)
  - Lejeune, Major General John A., 1925-1928 (Box 2)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1918-1919 (Box 2)
  - Longworth, Nicholas, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Maloney, Francis, Senator, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Marshall, Thomas, Vice President, undated (Box 2)
  - McAdoo, William Gibbs, Senator, 1937 (Box 2)
  - McCormick, Medill, 1917-1919; undated (Box 2)
  - McCumber, Porter J., Senator, 1922-1923 (Box 2)
  - McKellar, Kenneth, Senator, 1943 (Box 2)
  - McNary, Charles L., Senator, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Metcalf, Jesse H., Senator, 1925-1928; 1930,; 1932,; 1936,; undated (Box 2)
  - Moses, George H., Senator, 1923 (Box 2)
  - N-R, 1917; 1918,; 1924-1926,; 1930,; 1932,; 1933,; 1935-1937,; 1940 (Box 2)
  - New, Harry S., Senator, 1918 (Box 2)
  - Newberry, Truman H., Senator, 1921-1922; 1936 (Box 2)
  - Nye, Gerald P., Senator, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Payne, John Barton, 1919; 1922,; 1927 (Box 2)
  - Pepper, Claude, Senator, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Pepper, George, Senator, 1922 (Box 2)
  - Phelan, James D, 1918-1923 (Box 2)
  - Pittman, Key, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Ransdell, Joseph E., Senator, 1917; 1920 (Box 2)
  - Roberts, Kenneth, 1933-1935 (Box 2)
  - Robinson, Joe E., Senator, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Roosevelt, Kermit, 1930-1931 (Box 2)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1919; 1923,; 1924 (Box 2)
  - S-W, 1917-1923; 1926-1929,; 1931,; 1933-1939 (Box 2)
  - Samson, Flem D., 1928-1931 (Box 2)
  - Saulsbury, Willard, 1919-1920 (Box 2)
  - Sheppard, Morris, Senator, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Smathers, William H., 1938 (Box 2)
  - Spencer, Selden P., Senator, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Stimson, Henry L., 1929 (Box 2)
  - Taber, John, Senator, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Taft, Robert A., Senator, 1938-1939 (Box 2)
  - Townsend, John G. Jr., Senator, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Tydings, Millard E., 1929 (Box 2)
  - Vandenberg, Arthur H., Senator, 1931; 1935,; 1937 (Box 2)
  - Walcott, Frederick C., Senator, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Weller, O.E., Senator, 1927 (Box 2)
  - Wolcott, Josiah O., Senator, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified (Box 2)
- Manuscripts
  - Unidentified (Box 2)
- Published material
  - Newspaper Clipping about, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Speech by, in Congressional Record, 1927 (Box 2)